<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="comments.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Documentation User Comments</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>The Tomcat documentation integrates the
<a href="https://comments.apache.org/help.html">Apache Comments System</a>.
It allows users to add comments to most documentation pages. The comments
section can be found at the end of each page.</p>

</section>

<section name="Allowed Content">

<p>Please use the Apache Comments System responsibly. We can only provide
this service to the community as long as it isn't misused.</p>

<p>The comments are not for general Q&amp;A.
Comments should be pointed towards suggestions on improving the documentation
or server. Questions on how to use Apache Tomcat should be directed
to our <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/lists.html">mailing lists</a>.</p>

<p>Comments may be removed by moderators if they are either
implemented or considered invalid/off-topic.</p>

<p>HTML is not allowed in comments, and will just display as raw source code
if attempted. Links that do not point to an Apache site (*.apache.org) will
need approval by a moderator before the comment is visible to regular visitors.</p>

</section>

<section name="License">

<p>Any submitted comments must be contributed under the terms of the
<a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache License, Version 2.0</a>.</p>

</section>

<section name="Verified Users">

<p>Verified users gain the Apache feather next to their name,
and may post comments with links in them without requiring approval
by a moderator before the comments are shown. Being a verified user
in itself does not give you moderating rights. If you are interested
in becoming a verified user, please contact us on the
<a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/lists.html#tomcat-users">users mailing list</a>.</p>

<p>All ASF committers are automatically verified users.</p>

</section>

<section name="Moderators">

<p>Moderators are allowed to mark comments as "Resolved", "Invalid"
or "Sticky", remove marks, approve comments e.g. if they contain
a link, and delete comments. Moderators can also subscribe to new
comments and comment updates and use the dashboard to gain some
overview over all comments of a site.</p>

<p>To use the moderation features, you need to login to the comments
system. Furthermore you will need to allow cookies to be set for
comments.apache.org (this is done using a secure https cookie). Once
logged in as a moderator you will see additional moderation
options attached to each comment.</p>

<p>If you are a long time follower of the Apache Tomcat projects
and you are interested in becoming a moderator, please contact us on the
<a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/lists.html#tomcat-users">users mailing list</a>.</p>

</section>

<section name="Privacy Policy">

<p>No data except what you personally submit is kept on record.
A cookie is used to keep track of moderators and other people
who wish to create an account to avoid having to enter their
credentials whenever they wish to post a comment.</p>

<p>To prevent spam and unsolicited comments, we use a digest of
visitors' IPs to keep track of comments posted by them.</p>

<p>Entering an email address when you post a comment is completely
optional, and will not be shared with anyone. If you enter an
email address, it will be used to notify you when someone posts
a reply to one of your comments, provided you have registered
an account and validated your email address.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
