<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="ajp.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <author email="arjaquith@mindspring.com">Andrew R. Jaquith</author>
    <title>The AJP Connector</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>AJP Connector</strong> element represents a
  <strong>Connector</strong> component that communicates with a web
  connector via the <code>AJP</code> protocol.  This is used for cases
  where you wish to invisibly integrate Tomcat into an existing (or new)
  Apache installation, and you want Apache to handle the static content
  contained in the web application, and/or utilize Apache's SSL
  processing.</p>

  <p>This connector supports load balancing when used in conjunction with
  the <code>jvmRoute</code> attribute of the
  <a href="engine.html">Engine</a>.</p>

  <p>The native connectors supported with this Tomcat release are:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>JK 1.2.x with any of the supported servers. See
      <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/connectors-doc/">the JK docs</a>
      for details.</li>
      <li>mod_proxy on Apache httpd 2.x (included by default in Apache HTTP
      Server 2.2), with AJP enabled: see
      <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_proxy_ajp.html">the
      httpd docs</a> for details.</li>
    </ul>

  <p><b>Other native connectors supporting AJP may work, but are no longer
  supported.</b></p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

  <p>All implementations of <strong>Connector</strong>
  support the following attributes:</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="ajpFlush" required="false">
      <p>A boolean value which can be used to enable or disable sending
      AJP flush messages to the fronting proxy whenever an explicit
      flush happens. The default value is <code>true</code>.<br/>
      An AJP flush message is a SEND_BODY_CHUNK packet with no body content.
      Proxy implementations like mod_jk or mod_proxy_ajp will flush the
      data buffered in the web server to the client when they receive
      such a packet. Setting this to <code>false</code> can reduce
      AJP packet traffic but might delay sending packets to the client.
      At the end of the response, AJP does always flush to the client.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="allowTrace" required="false">
      <p>A boolean value which can be used to enable or disable the TRACE
      HTTP method. If not specified, this attribute is set to false.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="asyncTimeout" required="false">
      <p>The default timeout for asynchronous requests in milliseconds. If not
      specified, this attribute is set to 10000 (10 seconds).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="enableLookups" required="false">
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want calls to
      <code>request.getRemoteHost()</code> to perform DNS lookups in
      order to return the actual host name of the remote client.  Set
      to <code>false</code> to skip the DNS lookup and return the IP
      address in String form instead (thereby improving performance).
      By default, DNS lookups are disabled.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxHeaderCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of headers in a request that are allowed by the
      container. A request that contains more headers than the specified limit
      will be rejected. A value of less than 0 means no limit.
      If not specified, a default of 100 is used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxParameterCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of parameter and value pairs (GET plus POST) which
      will be automatically parsed by the container. Parameter and value pairs
      beyond this limit will be ignored. A value of less than 0 means no limit.
      If not specified, a default of 10000 is used. Note that
      <code>FailedRequestFilter</code> <a href="filter.html">filter</a> can be
      used to reject requests that hit the limit.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxPostSize" required="false">
      <p>The maximum size in bytes of the POST which will be handled by
      the container FORM URL parameter parsing. The limit can be disabled by
      setting this attribute to a value less than zero. If not specified, this
      attribute is set to 2097152 (2 megabytes). Note that the
      <a href="filter.html#Failed_Request_Filter"><code>FailedRequestFilter</code></a>
      can be used to reject requests that exceed this limit.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxSavePostSize" required="false">
      <p>The maximum size in bytes of the POST which will be saved/buffered by
      the container during FORM or CLIENT-CERT authentication. For both types
      of authentication, the POST will be saved/buffered before the user is
      authenticated. For CLIENT-CERT authentication, the POST is buffered for
      the duration of the SSL handshake and the buffer emptied when the request
      is processed. For FORM authentication the POST is saved whilst the user
      is re-directed to the login form and is retained until the user
      successfully authenticates or the session associated with the
      authentication request expires. The limit can be disabled by setting this
      attribute to -1. Setting the attribute to zero will disable the saving of
      POST data during authentication. If not specified, this attribute is set
      to 4096 (4 kilobytes).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="parseBodyMethods" required="false">
      <p>A comma-separated list of HTTP methods for which request
      bodies will be parsed for request parameters identically
      to POST. This is useful in RESTful applications that want to
      support POST-style semantics for PUT requests.
      Note that any setting other than <code>POST</code> causes Tomcat
      to behave in a way that goes against the intent of the servlet
      specification.
      The HTTP method TRACE is specifically forbidden here in accordance
      with the HTTP specification.
      The default is <code>POST</code></p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="port" required="true">
      <p>The TCP port number on which this <strong>Connector</strong>
      will create a server socket and await incoming connections.  Your
      operating system will allow only one server application to listen
      to a particular port number on a particular IP address. If the special
      value of 0 (zero) is used, then Tomcat will select a free port at random
      to use for this connector. This is typically only useful in embedded and
      testing applications.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="protocol" required="false">
      <p>Sets the protocol to handle incoming traffic. To configure an AJP
        connector this must be specified. If no value for protocol is provided,
        an <a href="http.html">HTTP connector</a> rather than an AJP connector
        will be configured.<br/>
        The standard protocol value for an AJP connector is <code>AJP/1.3</code>
        which uses an auto-switching mechanism to select either a Java based
        connector or an APR/native based connector. If the
        <code>PATH</code> (Windows) or <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> (on most unix
        systems) environment variables contain the Tomcat native library, the
        native/APR connector will be used. If the native library cannot be
        found, the Java BIO based connector will be used.<br/>
        To use an explicit protocol rather than rely on the auto-switching
        mechanism described above, the following values may be used:<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.ajp.AjpProtocol</code>
        - blocking Java connector<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.ajp.AjpNioProtocol</code>
        - non blocking Java connector.<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.ajp.AjpAprProtocol</code>
        - the APR/native connector.<br/>
        Custom implementations may also be used.<br/>
        Take a look at our <a href="#Connector_Comparison">Connector
        Comparison</a> chart.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="proxyName" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is being used in a proxy
      configuration, configure this attribute to specify the server name
      to be returned for calls to <code>request.getServerName()</code>.
      See <a href="#Proxy_Support">Proxy Support</a> for more
      information.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="proxyPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is being used in a proxy
      configuration, configure this attribute to specify the server port
      to be returned for calls to <code>request.getServerPort()</code>.
      See <a href="#Proxy_Support">Proxy Support</a> for more
      information.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="redirectPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is supporting non-SSL
      requests, and a request is received for which a matching
      <code>&lt;security-constraint&gt;</code> requires SSL transport,
      Catalina will automatically redirect the request to the port
      number specified here.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="scheme" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to the name of the protocol you wish to have
      returned by calls to <code>request.getScheme()</code>.  For
      example, you would set this attribute to "<code>https</code>"
      for an SSL Connector.  The default value is "<code>http</code>".
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="secure" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> if you wish to have
      calls to <code>request.isSecure()</code> to return <code>true</code>
      for requests received by this Connector. You would want this on an
      SSL Connector or a non SSL connector that is receiving data from a
      SSL accelerator, like a crypto card, a SSL appliance or even a webserver.
      The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="URIEncoding" required="false">
      <p>This specifies the character encoding used to decode the URI bytes,
      after %xx decoding the URL. If not specified, ISO-8859-1 will be used.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="useBodyEncodingForURI" required="false">
      <p>This specifies if the encoding specified in contentType should be used
      for URI query parameters, instead of using the URIEncoding. This
      setting is present for compatibility with Tomcat 4.1.x, where the
      encoding specified in the contentType, or explicitly set using
      Request.setCharacterEncoding method was also used for the parameters from
      the URL. The default value is <code>false</code>.
      </p>
      <p><em>Notes:</em> See notes on this attribute in
      <a href="http.html">HTTP Connector</a> documentation.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="useIPVHosts" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> to cause Tomcat to use
      the IP address passed by the native web server to determine the Host
      to send the request to.  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="xpoweredBy" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> to cause Tomcat to advertise
      support for the Servlet specification using the header recommended in the
      specification.  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Standard Implementations">

  <p>To use AJP, you must specify the protocol attribute (see above).</p>

  <p>The standard AJP connectors (BIO, NIO and APR/native) all support the
  following attributes in addition to the common Connector attributes listed
  above.</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="acceptCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum queue length for incoming connection requests when
      all possible request processing threads are in use.  Any requests
      received when the queue is full will be refused.  The default
      value is 100.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="acceptorThreadCount" required="false">
      <p>The number of threads to be used to accept connections. Increase this
      value on a multi CPU machine, although you would never really need more
      than <code>2</code>. Also, with a lot of non keep alive connections, you
      might want to increase this value as well. Default value is
      <code>1</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="acceptorThreadPriority" required="false">
      <p>The priority of the acceptor threads. The threads used to accept
      new connections. The default value is <code>5</code> (the value of the
      <code>java.lang.Thread.NORM_PRIORITY</code> constant). See the JavaDoc
      for the <code>java.lang.Thread</code> class for more details on what
      this priority means.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="address" required="false">
      <p>For servers with more than one IP address, this attribute
      specifies which address will be used for listening on the specified
      port.  By default, this port will be used on all IP addresses
      associated with the server. A value of <code>127.0.0.1</code>
      indicates that the Connector will only listen on the loopback
      interface.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="bindOnInit" required="false">
      <p>Controls when the socket used by the connector is bound. By default it
      is bound when the connector is initiated and unbound when the connector is
      destroyed. If set to <code>false</code>, the socket will be bound when the
      connector is started and unbound when it is stopped.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="clientCertProvider" required="false">
      <p>When client certificate information is presented in a form other than
      instances of <code>java.security.cert.X509Certificate</code> it needs to
      be converted before it can be used and this property controls which JSSE
      provider is used to perform the conversion. For example it is used with
      the AJP connectors, the <a href="http.html">HTTP APR connector</a> and
      with the <a href="valve.html#SSL_Authenticator_Valve">
      org.apache.catalina.valves.SSLValve</a>.If not specified, the default
      provider will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="connectionLinger" required="false">
      <p>The number of seconds during which the sockets used by this
      <strong>Connector</strong> will linger when they are closed. The default
      value is <code>-1</code> which disables socket linger.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="connectionTimeout" required="false">
      <p>The number of milliseconds this <strong>Connector</strong> will wait,
      after accepting a connection, for the request URI line to be
      presented.  The default value for AJP protocol connectors
      is <code>-1</code> (i.e. infinite).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="executor" required="false">
      <p>A reference to the name in an <a href="executor.html">Executor</a>
      element. If this attribute is set, and the named executor exists, the
      connector will use the executor, and all the other thread attributes will
      be ignored. Note that if a shared executor is not specified for a
      connector then the connector will use a private, internal executor to
      provide the thread pool.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="executorTerminationTimeoutMillis" required="false">
      <p>The time that the private internal executor will wait for request
      processing threads to terminate before continuing with the process of
      stopping the connector. If not set, the default is <code>0</code> (zero)
      for the BIO connector and <code>5000</code> (5 seconds) for the NIO and
      APR/native connectors.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keepAliveTimeout" required="false">
      <p>The number of milliseconds this <strong>Connector</strong> will wait for
       another AJP request before closing the connection.
       The default value is to use the value that has been set for the
       connectionTimeout attribute.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxConnections" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of connections that the server will accept and
      process at any given time. When this number has been reached, the server
      will accept, but not process, one further connection. This additional
      connection be blocked until the number of connections being processed
      falls below <strong>maxConnections</strong> at which point the server will
      start accepting and processing new connections again. Note that once the
      limit has been reached, the operating system may still accept connections
      based on the <code>acceptCount</code> setting. The default value varies by
      connector type. For BIO the default is the value of
      <strong>maxThreads</strong> unless an <a href="executor.html">Executor</a>
      is used in which case the default will be the value of maxThreads from the
      executor. For NIO the default is <code>10000</code>.
      For APR/native, the default is <code>8192</code>.</p>
      <p>Note that for APR/native on Windows, the configured value will be
      reduced to the highest multiple of 1024 that is less than or equal to
      maxConnections. This is done for performance reasons.<br/>
      If set to a value of -1, the maxConnections feature is disabled 
      and connections are not counted.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxCookieCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of cookies that are permitted for a request. A value
      of less than zero means no limit. If not specified, a default value of 200
      will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxThreads" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of request processing threads to be created
      by this <strong>Connector</strong>, which therefore determines the
      maximum number of simultaneous requests that can be handled.  If
      not specified, this attribute is set to 200. If an executor is associated
      with this connector, this attribute is ignored as the connector will
      execute tasks using the executor rather than an internal thread pool. Note
      that if an executor is configured any value set for this attribute will be
      recorded correctly but it will be reported (e.g. via JMX) as
      <code>-1</code> to make clear that it is not used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="minSpareThreads" required="false">
      <p>The minimum number of threads always kept running. If not specified,
      the default of <code>10</code> is used. If an executor is associated
      with this connector, this attribute is ignored as the connector will
      execute tasks using the executor rather than an internal thread pool. Note
      that if an executor is configured any value set for this attribute will be
      recorded correctly but it will be reported (e.g. via JMX) as
      <code>-1</code> to make clear that it is not used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="packetSize" required="false">
      <p>This attribute sets the maximum AJP packet size in Bytes. The maximum
      value is 65536. It should be the same as the <code>max_packet_size</code>
      directive configured for mod_jk. Normally it is not necessary to change
      the maximum packet size. Problems with the default value have been
      reported when sending certificates or certificate chains. The default
      value is 8192. If set to less than 8192 then the setting will ignored and
      the default value of 8192 used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="processorCache" required="false">
      <p>The protocol handler caches Processor objects to speed up performance.
      This setting dictates how many of these objects get cached.
      <code>-1</code> means unlimited, default is <code>200</code>. If not using
      Servlet 3.0 asynchronous processing, a good default is to use the same as
      the maxThreads setting. If using Servlet 3.0 asynchronous processing, a
      good default is to use the larger of maxThreads and the maximum number of
      expected concurrent requests (synchronous and asynchronous).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="requiredSecret" required="false">
      <p>Only requests from workers with this secret keyword will be accepted.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="tcpNoDelay" required="false">
      <p>If set to <code>true</code>, the TCP_NO_DELAY option will be
      set on the server socket, which improves performance under most
      circumstances.  This is set to <code>true</code> by default.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="threadPriority" required="false">
      <p>The priority of the request processing threads within the JVM.
      The default value is <code>5</code> (the value of the
      <code>java.lang.Thread.NORM_PRIORITY</code> constant). See the JavaDoc
      for the <code>java.lang.Thread</code> class for more details on what
      this priority means.If an executor is associated
      with this connector, this attribute is ignored as the connector will
      execute tasks using the executor rather than an internal thread pool. Note
      that if an executor is configured any value set for this attribute will be
      recorded correctly but it will be reported (e.g. via JMX) as
      <code>-1</code> to make clear that it is not used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="tomcatAuthentication" required="false">
      <p>If set to <code>true</code>, the authentication will be done in Tomcat.
      Otherwise, the authenticated principal will be propagated from the native
      webserver and used for authorization in Tomcat. Note that this principal
      will have no roles associated with it.
      The default value is <code>true</code>. If
      <code>tomcatAuthorization</code> is set to <code>true</code> this
      attribute has no effect.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="tomcatAuthorization" required="false">
      <p>If set to <code>true</code>, the authenticated principal will be
      propagated from the native webserver and considered already authenticated
      in Tomcat. If the web application has one or more security constraints,
      authorization will then be performed by Tomcat and roles assigned to the
      authenticated principal. If the appropriate Tomcat Realm for the request
      does not recognise the provided user name, a Principal will be still be
      created but it will have no roles. The default value is
      <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Java TCP socket attributes">

    <p>The BIO and NIO implementation support the following Java TCP socket
    attributes in addition to the common Connector and HTTP attributes listed
    above.</p>

    <attributes>
      <attribute name="socket.rxBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The socket receive buffer (SO_RCVBUF) size in bytes. JVM default
        used if not set.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.txBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The socket send buffer (SO_SNDBUF) size in bytes. JVM default
        used if not set.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.tcpNoDelay" required="false">
        <p>(bool)This is equivalent to standard attribute
        <strong>tcpNoDelay</strong>.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soKeepAlive" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the socket's keep alive setting
        (SO_KEEPALIVE). JVM default used if not set.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.ooBInline" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the socket OOBINLINE setting. JVM default
        used if not set.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soReuseAddress" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the sockets reuse address option
        (SO_REUSEADDR). JVM default used if not set.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soLingerOn" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the sockets so linger option (SO_LINGER).
        A value for the standard attribute <strong>connectionLinger</strong>
        that is &gt;=0 is equivalent to setting this to <code>true</code>.
        A value for the standard attribute <strong>connectionLinger</strong>
        that is &lt;0 is equivalent to setting this to <code>false</code>.
        Both this attribute and <code>soLingerTime</code> must be set else the
        JVM defaults will be used for both.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soLingerTime" required="false">
        <p>(int)Value in seconds for the sockets so linger option (SO_LINGER).
        This is equivalent to standard attribute
        <strong>connectionLinger</strong>.
        Both this attribute and <code>soLingerOn</code> must be set else the
        JVM defaults will be used for both.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soTimeout" required="false">
        <p>This is equivalent to standard attribute
        <strong>connectionTimeout</strong>.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.performanceConnectionTime" required="false">
        <p>(int)The first value for the performance settings. See
        <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a>
        All three performance attributes must be set else the JVM defaults will
        be used for all three.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.performanceLatency" required="false">
        <p>(int)The second value for the performance settings. See
        <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a>
        All three performance attributes must be set else the JVM defaults will
        be used for all three.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.performanceBandwidth" required="false">
        <p>(int)The third value for the performance settings. See
        <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a>
        All three performance attributes must be set else the JVM defaults will
        be used for all three.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.unlockTimeout" required="false">
        <p>(int) The timeout for a socket unlock. When a connector is stopped, it will try to release the acceptor thread by opening a connector to itself.
           The default value is <code>250</code> and the value is in milliseconds</p>
      </attribute>
    </attributes>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="NIO specific configuration">

    <p>The following attributes are specific to the NIO connector.</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="socket.directBuffer" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value, whether to use direct ByteBuffers or java mapped
        ByteBuffers. Default is <code>false</code>.<br/>
        When you are using direct buffers, make sure you allocate the
        appropriate amount of memory for the direct memory space. On Sun's JDK
        that would be something like <code>-XX:MaxDirectMemorySize=256m</code>.
        </p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.appReadBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)Each connection that is opened up in Tomcat get associated with
        a read ByteBuffer. This attribute controls the size of this buffer. By
        default this read buffer is sized at <code>8192</code> bytes. For lower
        concurrency, you can increase this to buffer more data. For an extreme
        amount of keep alive connections, decrease this number or increase your
        heap size.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.appWriteBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)Each connection that is opened up in Tomcat get associated with
        a write ByteBuffer. This attribute controls the size of this buffer. By
        default this write buffer is sized at <code>8192</code> bytes. For low
        concurrency you can increase this to buffer more response data. For an
        extreme amount of keep alive connections, decrease this number or
        increase your heap size.<br/>
        The default value here is pretty low, you should up it if you are not
        dealing with tens of thousands concurrent connections.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.bufferPool" required="false">
        <p>(int)The NIO connector uses a class called NioChannel that holds
        elements linked to a socket. To reduce garbage collection, the NIO
        connector caches these channel objects. This value specifies the size of
        this cache. The default value is <code>500</code>, and represents that
        the cache will hold 500 NioChannel objects. Other values are
        <code>-1</code> for unlimited cache and <code>0</code> for no cache.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.bufferPoolSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The NioChannel pool can also be size based, not used object
        based. The size is calculated as follows:<br/>
        NioChannel
        <code>buffer size = read buffer size + write buffer size</code><br/>
        SecureNioChannel <code>buffer size = application read buffer size +
        application write buffer size + network read buffer size +
        network write buffer size</code><br/>
        The value is in bytes, the default value is <code>1024*1024*100</code>
        (100MB).</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.processorCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache SocketProcessor objects to reduce garbage
        collection. The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the
        cache at most. The default is <code>500</code>. Other values are
        <code>-1</code> for unlimited cache and <code>0</code> for no cache.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.keyCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache KeyAttachment objects to reduce garbage
        collection. The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the
        cache at most. The default is <code>500</code>. Other values are
        <code>-1</code> for unlimited cache and <code>0</code> for no cache.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="socket.eventCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache PollerEvent objects to reduce garbage
        collection. The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the
        cache at most. The default is <code>500</code>. Other values are
        <code>-1</code> for unlimited cache and <code>0</code> for no cache.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="selectorPool.maxSelectors" required="false">
        <p>(int)The max selectors to be used in the pool, to reduce selector
        contention. Use this option when the command line
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared</code> value is set
        to false. Default value is <code>200</code>.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="selectorPool.maxSpareSelectors" required="false">
        <p>(int)The max spare selectors to be used in the pool, to reduce
        selector contention. When a selector is returned to the pool, the system
        can decide to keep it or let it be GC'd. Use this option when the
        command line <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared</code>
        value is set to false. Default value is <code>-1</code> (unlimited).</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="command-line-options" required="false">
        <p>The following command line options are available for the NIO
        connector:<br/>
        <code>-Dorg.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared=true|false</code>
        - default is <code>true</code>. Set this value to <code>false</code> if you wish to
        use a selector for each thread. When you set it to <code>false</code>, you can
        control the size of the pool of selectors by using the
        <strong>selectorPool.maxSelectors</strong> attribute.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="APR/native specific configuration">

    <p>The APR/native implementation supports the following attributes in
    addition to the common Connector and AJP attributes listed above.</p>

    <attributes>
      <attribute name="pollTime" required="false">
        <p>Duration of a poll call in microseconds. Lowering this value will
        slightly decrease latency of connections being kept alive in some cases
        , but will use more CPU as more poll calls are being made. The default
        value is 2000 (2ms).
        </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="pollerSize" required="false">
      <p>Amount of sockets that the poller responsible for polling kept alive
      connections can hold at a given time. Extra connections will be closed
      right away. The default value is 8192, corresponding to 8192 keep-alive
      connections.</p>
    </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p>None at this time.</p>

</section>

<section name="Special Features">

  <subsection name="Proxy Support">

  <p>The <code>proxyName</code> and <code>proxyPort</code> attributes can
  be used when Tomcat is run behind a proxy server.  These attributes
  modify the values returned to web applications that call the
  <code>request.getServerName()</code> and <code>request.getServerPort()</code>
  methods, which are often used to construct absolute URLs for redirects.
  Without configuring these attributes, the values returned would reflect
  the server name and port on which the connection from the proxy server
  was received, rather than the server name and port to whom the client
  directed the original request.</p>

  <p>For more information, see the
  <a href="../proxy-howto.html">Proxy Support HOW-TO</a>.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Connector Comparison">

    <p>Below is a small chart that shows how the connectors differ.</p>
    <source>
                       Java Blocking Connector   Java Nio Blocking Connector   APR/native Connector
                                 BIO                         NIO                       APR
    Classname                AjpProtocol               AjpNioProtocol           AjpAprProtocol
    Tomcat Version           3.x onwards                 7.x onwards              5.5.x onwards
    Support Polling              NO                          YES                       YES
    Polling Size                 N/A                   maxConnections             maxConnections
    Read Request Headers      Blocking                    Blocking                   Blocking
    Read Request Body         Blocking                    Blocking                   Blocking
    Write Response            Blocking                    Blocking                   Blocking
    Wait for next Request     Blocking                  Non Blocking               Non Blocking
    Max Connections        maxConnections              maxConnections             maxConnections

    </source>

  </subsection>

</section>

</body>

</document>
