<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="connectors.html">

    &project;

    <properties>
        <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
        <title>Connectors How To</title>
    </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>Choosing a connector to use with Tomcat can be difficult. This page will
list the connectors which are supported with this Tomcat release, and will
hopefully help you make the right choice according to your needs.</p>

</section>

<section name="HTTP">

<p>The HTTP connector is setup by default with Tomcat, and is ready to use. This
connector features the lowest latency and best overall performance.</p>

<p>For clustering, a HTTP load balancer <b>with support for web sessions stickiness</b>
must be installed to direct the traffic to the Tomcat servers. Tomcat supports mod_proxy
(on Apache HTTP Server 2.x, and included by default in Apache HTTP Server 2.2) as the load balancer.
It should be noted that the performance of HTTP proxying is usually lower than the
performance of AJP, so AJP clustering is often preferable.</p>

</section>

<section name="AJP">

<p>When using a single server, the performance when using a native webserver in
front of the Tomcat instance is most of the time significantly worse than a
standalone Tomcat with its default HTTP connector, even if a large part of the web
application is made of static files. If integration with the native webserver is
needed for any reason, an AJP connector will provide faster performance than
proxied HTTP. AJP clustering is the most efficient from the Tomcat perspective.
It is otherwise functionally equivalent to HTTP clustering.</p>

<p>The native connectors supported with this Tomcat release are:</p>
<ul>
<li>JK 1.2.x with any of the supported servers</li>
<li>mod_proxy on Apache HTTP Server 2.x (included by default in Apache HTTP Server 2.2),
with AJP enabled</li>
</ul>

<p><b>Other native connectors supporting AJP may work, but are no longer supported.</b></p>

</section>

</body>

</document>
